Hello there. This is
our fourth lecture on
respiratory physiology,
and today we're going
to explore transport
of gases in blood and
tissue fluids. My name
is Dr. Yerke Lee Hest.
The session objectives
are consistent with the
event description,
which is that this event
focuses on the components
and mechanisms that
facilitate transport of
oxygen and CO2 throughout
the body and that ensure
proper delivery or
release at the right
time in the right places.
This image illustrates how
the main gases that we're
concerned with, namely
oxygen and carbon dioxide,
are moving around in our body.
So the majority of oxygen
is bound to hemoglobin,
about 98.5%, and a
much smaller portion,
only 1.5% are freely
dissolved in plasma.
Different texts have
slightly different numbers,
but what you see here
is from Constanzos.
with carbon dioxide it's
a little bit different so
here the majority of carbon
dioxide moves around in our
bloodstream in the form
of the bicarbonate buffer
system then 30 percent are
bound to hemoglobin to a
different site than oxygen is
and then 10 percent are freely
dissolved so those 10
percent are about 6.7 times
more than oxygen and the
reason for it is that carbon
dioxide is much more soluble
in water than oxygen is.
So the big question
remains, if some oxygen
can be dissolved in
plasma, why go through all
of the bother to put red
blood cells together?
Well, let's see what would
happen if our body could
only rely on freely
dissolved oxygen. So the
concentration of oxygen
at 100 millimeters mercury
is about 0.3 milliliters of
oxygen per 100 milliliters
of blood. So that number
I got from Henry's
Law, and that's how I
arrived at 0.3 milliliters.
Why are we looking at
100 millimeters mercury?
Well, that's the partial
pressure of oxygen in
freshly oxygenated blood
as it leaves the lungs. So
that's the most there ever
is in our bloodstream.
How do we convert
this to the amount or
volume of blood in the
human body? Well, that
is about 6 liters or
6,000 milliliters.
So basically, we have
to multiply these 100
milliliters by 60 to
arrive at 6 liters. And if
we do that, then the
total of oxygen that
would be available is
15 milliliters of oxygen
per minute if it was
just dissolved in plasma.
Now, how does that compare
to the need of our body?
Well, the need is around
250 milliliters of oxygen
per minute needed to
function, and that's at rest.
So you can see that that's a
huge difference, about 13-fold.
So this value without
hemoglobin and red
blood cells would not
be consistent with life.
There's one other thing I
would like to point out,
and I've mentioned it before.
When we talk about partial
pressures, you have to
remember, and that's really,
really important, that
only the freely dissolved
gases are part of the partial
pressure consideration.
So anything that's bound to
hemoglobin is not part of
the partial pressure that's
measured when measuring
partial pressure of oxygen.
It is only what's dissolved.
With carbon dioxide, it's a
little bit more complicated
because what's not
considered is what's bound
directly to hemoglobin, but
what is considered part of
the partial pressure is
what's freely dissolved and
also what's part of the
bicarbonate buffer system
because that is freely in
solution in plasma as well.
the only component of the
system that is bound to
the red blood cell is the
carbonic anhydrase. So that's
the enzyme that makes the
conversion of the molecules
that are part of the
bicarbonate buffer system.
The CO2 that's part of the
bicarbonate buffer system
is considered freely
dissolved. So that's 60
factors into the partial
pressure of carbon dioxide.
Here we're taking
a look at the adult
form of hemoglobin,
also designated HbA.
So that's A stands for
adult. And adult hemoglobin
consists of four protein
chains. There are two
beta chains and two alpha
chains. Each of them have
a heme portion, a heme
group associated with them.
And it is this heme group
that binds the oxygen.
So I love this illustration
because alpha and
beta chains and
the heme group which
contains an iron
atom are beautifully
illustrated.
So when this hemoglobin
picks up oxygen it turns
into oxyhemoglobin and
when it unloads oxygen
and is deoxygenated, it
turns into deoxyhemoglobin.
And keep in mind for
the later part of this
lecture that these two
forms of hemoglobin have a
different spectral pattern
when you shine certain
forms of light on it,
which will become important
in the measurement of
oxygenation of blood.
Here we're looking at
fetal hemoglobin, which is
very similar compared to
adult hemoglobin. However,
instead of two beta
chains, fetal hemoglobin
has two gamma chains. So
you can see this here,
that's a gamma chain,
one right here, but also
has two alpha chains like
the adult hemoglobin.
So this is the adult
version. Adult has 2
-alpha, 2-beta. Fetal
has 2-alpha and 2-gamma.
Now, why do fetuses
feature a different type
of hemoglobin? Well,
the short answer is that
fetal hemoglobin has a
higher affinity to oxygen,
and it does not interact
with 2,3-BPG, which
is a metabolite that
comes out of glycolysis.
Overall, this fetal
hemoglobin has a higher
affinity for oxygen,
and it has to because
the fetus doesn't
breathe, so it relies on
extracting oxygen from
the maternal blood. So
its hemoglobin has to
have a higher affinity
to pull oxygen off the
maternal blood supply.
Let's look at some dysfunctional
oxygen transporters.
So here we have a
red blood cell that's
filled with methemoglobin
instead of hemoglobin.
And methemoglobin has a
central iron atom that has
been oxidized, and it's
in the Fe3 plus state,
whereas the normal
hemoglobin that can interact
with oxygen is Fe2 plus.
So there are congenital
reasons for this. There are
acquired reasons. Acquired
reasons can be oxidative
stress, for instance.
It can also be
certain medications,
such as certain
anti-malarial drugs.
A person who is suffering
from methemoglobinemia appears
fatigued and can have a
bluish tint to their skin
and their other signs and
symptoms. but the good thing
is that this condition is
reversible and that's what
those two arrows here are
indicating this is sickle cell
hemoglobin which is a
version of hemoglobin that
carries a mutation in the
hemoglobin beta chain where a
glutamic acid is mutated
into valine amino acid that
slightly changes the
conformation of the sickle cell
hemoglobin. And the red blood
cell that results from this
and is packed with sickle
cell hemoglobin not only
has a lower oxygen carrying
capacity, it also destabilizes
in shape, especially under
oxygen-poor conditions.
So that wears the
hemoglobin out much faster,
and that causes a
whole host of issues.
This mutation is particularly
prevalent in certain
parts of the world where
malaria is prevalent,
and the pathogen for it
hides in red blood cells,
and therefore having
a mutation and being
heterozygous for it is
actually a genetic advantage.
But it comes for the price of,
as far as we're concerned,
a lower oxygen affinity.
Let's now look at two
different concepts,
and that is the oxygen binding
capacity versus oxygen content.
So this looks complicated,
but the oxygen binding
capacity describes the amount
of oxygen that can be
maximally bound by hemoglobin.
That's all of this here. And
let's see how much that is.
Well,
one gram of hemoglobin
A, that's adult
hemoglobin, can bind 1
.34 milliliters of oxygen.
So how much adult
hemoglobin do we have in
blood? We have about 15
grams per 100 milliliters.
So if you then multiply
15 times 134, you end
up with 20.1 milliliters
of oxygen that can be
maximally bound to 100
millimeters of blood.
And that oxygen, once again,
is bound to hemoglobin.
It's not the one that
is freely dissolved.
That brings us to
the second concept,
and that is the oxygen content.
So the oxygen content
is different because it
considers all types of oxygen
that are associated with
blood. So the actual
amount of oxygen in blood.
So that considers the
oxygen binding capacity.
So remember, the binding
capacity is the maximum.
So in order to get to the
real content, you have to
multiply the maximally
possible amount of oxygen with
the saturation percentage.
So let's say that's 95%, then
you multiply the 20.1 times
0.95, and then in the end
you add the dissolved oxygen,
which is something that
we didn't consider with the
oxygen binding capacity.
This slide illustrates
the considerations
that need to be
made when talking
about oxygen
delivery to tissues.
We already know that the
oxygen content of blood
is the sum of dissolved
oxygen, which is around
2%, and oxygen bound to
hemoglobin, which is around
98%. So how do we get
from that to the amount
of oxygen that's being
delivered to tissues? Well,
we have to factor in
cardiac output, of course.
So oxygen delivery is
defined as the cardiac
output, so the blood moved
by the heart, multiplied
with the oxygen content,
which once again is
the product of its
dissolved version plus the
version bind to hemoglobin.
That's actually a very
clever little illustration
here if you want to
take the time and have a
closer look for drivers.
On this slide, you can
appreciate the oxygen hemoglobin
dissociation curve,
and one thing that you
notice right away is that
the shape is not linear but
it's sigmoidal. So that
means that oxygen affinity
depends very much on the
oxygen concentration in
the environment and
that's what we've plotted
here. So we've plotted
the hemoglobin saturation
percent versus the partial
pressure of oxygen in a
certain area in the body
and you can see that
where the oxygen concentration
in the body is high
hemoglobin is very much
saturated and so then you as
we follow the line you
can see that the partial
pressure of oxygen actually
drops quite a bit all the
way down to 50 so and so
if the partial pressure of
oxygen is at 50 so that would
be right here which means
that it has the environment
has given up 50% of
the initial 100%, then
still 85% of all hemoglobin
molecules are still loaded
with oxygen. So that means
that most hemoglobin molecules
that are in this zone
either have three or still all
four of their oxygen molecules.
So now we move further
down the line, and
then we get to a point
that's called P50.
So P50 is the point
where we see 50% of
oxygen saturation of
hemoglobin. And at that
point, in order for
hemoglobin to release
two of its four,
that's what 50% means,
oxygen molecules, the
partial pressure of oxygen
in that particular
environment has to be
already super low, and at
25 millimeters mercury.
And I told you before
that that typically
doesn't happen.
So the lowest we
normally see in our
bodies is around 40.
So, another point worth
mentioning is that this
sigmoidal behavior, this
behavior of hemoglobin to
respond very much to
environmental oxygen concentration
is due to the positive
cooperativity of the binding
of oxygen to hemoglobin.
So in other words,
hemoglobin that is largely
saturated holds on very
tightly to its oxygen, and
hemoglobin that is largely
unsaturated very easily
or comparatively easily
gives off its oxygen. So
how does that matter? Well,
an example of this would be
blood with its hemoglobin
running through the
lungs, where it has just
taken up oxygen and bound
to hemoglobin. So there's
no need for the hemoglobin
to unload oxygen, and
the sigmoidal shape of
this curve indicates that.
This slide compares
and contrasts
the loading and
unloading of oxygen.
So when we have a
fully oxygenated
hemoglobin, we call
that oxyhemoglobin.
And once oxyhemoglobin
unloads oxygen,
we consider that
deoxyhemoglobin.
So we have more
deoxyhemoglobin here than here.
This here happens at a partial
pressure of oxygen of 100 mmHg.
That's right after
the blood has
been fully loaded with oxygen.
Here we are the
P40 value, and as
I told you in our
previous slide,
that is about as low
as it gets in our body.
How can we take
advantage of it,
of having this knowledge? Well,
some very clever people
developed the pulse oximetry
method, and it's a little
device that gets put
onto our finger, and it basically
measures the oxygenation
status of arterial blood
in our finger. And it
uses dual wavelength, so
it can distinguish between
fully oxygenated hemoglobin
and partially oxygenated
or deoxygenated hemoglobin.
And then from the
percentage of one versus
the other, it calculates the
arterial partial pressure
of oxygen. Very clever.
So how can the
system of loading and
unloading hemoglobin
be made most efficient?
Well, you can see this here.
The hemoglobin dissociation
curve can be shifted
either to the right, so
the shifted line is the
dotted line, or it can
be shifted to the left.
If it's shifted to the
right, let's go to our P50
value, where 50% of the
hemoglobin is oxygenated.
We can see that upon
right shift, that
happens at a
partial pressure of
around 40 millimeters
mercury of oxygen.
So if there was no right shift,
then we take our P50
value here, we go down
here. That means that
without a right shift,
hemoglobin would only let
go of the same amount of
oxygen at a much lower
partial pressure of oxygen.
So in order for those
muscles in those
areas without right
shift to get to the
oxygen, the oxygen
partial pressure needs to
drop to 25 milliliters
mercury or below.
So with our right shift,
the letting go happens at
a higher partial pressure,
which overall means
that right shifting makes
it easier for hemoglobin
to unload oxygen. Left
shifting does the opposite.
So here again at P50.
And so upon left shift,
the oxygen is let go at a
partial pressure of around
12 and a half. I would
say if it wasn't left
shifted, then we extrapolate
the P50 to the actual non
-shifted line. So the oxygen
would be let go at a much
higher or significantly
higher partial pressure
of oxygen in the blood.
So when do we experience left
and right shift? Well, Well,
left shift, making things
easier to let go of
oxygen, makes a lot of
sense in active tissues.
So active tissues,
they consume a lot of
energy and oxygen. So
in those active tissues,
like big muscles, the
partial pressure of
carbon dioxide is high
and the pH is low.
So that's together we
call the Bohr effect.
Active muscle also heats
up. So, it makes sense
then that ride shift occurs
in warmer temperatures.
Also, there's this chemical
that's part of glycolysis.
It's actually intermediate,
and it's called 2,3-DPG.
And tissues that are
highly active in glycolysis
are deemed to be highly
active and need more
oxygen. So if this molecule
is around in abundance,
it's also a signal
for the system to make
it easier for hemoglobin
to release its oxygen.
Pretty much the opposite
is true for the left shift.
So those applies then to
tissues in the lung that
are nearby the site where
the blood has been just
re-oxygenated. it would
apply to parts of the body
that are metabolically
not very active and it's
pretty much the reverse of
what we've just discussed.
One word of caution, this all
applies to adult hemoglobin.
So in other words,
fetal hemoglobin does
not use 2,3-DPG. So
please keep that in
mind, that's going to
come up again later.
So what are the conditions
that could interfere
with the process that
we just discussed?
Well, one of the chemicals
that can do that is carbon
monoxide because it
competitively binds with the
same site that oxygen
binds to on hemoglobin. The
problem is that carbon
monoxide binds more than 200
times tighter than oxygen,
and it's really, really
difficult to get off. So
in this example here, we're
comparing a normal oxygen
hemoglobin dissociation curve
with one that somebody
encounters after carbon
monoxide poisoning. So this
person is lucky because
this person only experienced
carbon monoxide for a
certain amount of time,
basically saturating 50% of
azimoglobin with carbon
monoxide instead of oxygen. So
anything more would be
really difficult and would
produce a state that's not
consistent with survival.
So what do you do with
somebody that this happens to?
Well, here are the therapies
that are currently used.
So if depending on the
phenotypical situation
on the presentation.
If time is not at the essence,
then regular air
at five hours will
suffice to get rid of
the carbon monoxide.
Oftentimes, however, air
saturated with O2 is used to
just increase the
concentration gradient to drive
carbon monoxide away from the
oxygen binding sites that's
applied for one and a
half hours and in extreme
cases a person can be sent
into hyperbaric chamber which
operates under three
atmospheres with the according
oxygen concentration for
about 20 minutes so please
all make sure that you have
a carbon monoxide alarm
in your in the
place where you live
especially where you
sleep it's poisonous gas
it can kill and it
does kill every year.
How else can the body
respond to oxygen
delivery shortages
in ways other
than what we have
already looked at?
So one works through a
glycoprotein, that's a
hormone, it's called
erythropoietin and abbreviated
EPO, and it's mainly
reduced in the kidneys,
but also to some lesser
degree in the liver.
And the trigger for it
is hypoxia. For instance,
at high altitudes, the
oxygen concentration in
air is much lower, and
then over time this process
happens here, which
ends with EPO synthesis.
Then EPO travels to
the bone marrow, binds
to proerythroblasts,
increases their number,
and also facilitates
differentiation of
proerythroblasts into
mature erythrocytes.
So in this way,
the amount of red
blood cells has
just been increased.
So why is the kidney a
good organ to do this work?
Well, the answer is that the
kidney has sensing capabilities
that allow it to distinguish
between true oxygen
shortage and reduced blood
flow. As simple as that.
Now we've spoken a
lot about oxygen,
but how about carbon dioxide?
So from the earlier
slides, we know
that a minority of
carbon dioxide is
actually carried and
bound by hemoglobin.
It's a different site
than the oxygen binding
site, so they're not
competitive, but they
can sense each other.
So and that will become
important towards the
end of the presentation.
The majority of carbon
dioxide is actually moved in
blood as part of the
bicarbonate buffer system. So
we're talking about 80% or
more, and there's only a
small amount of hemoglobin.
I'm sorry, small amount
of carbon dioxide that's
freely dissolved in blood.
So and depending on the
source you're reading, it's
anywhere between 5 and 10%.
The main sources for this
lecture indicate that it's
around 5%. So what you do is
that consideration that 2.8
milliliters of carbon dioxide
can be freely carried by
100 milliliters of blood.
How do we get there? Well
we look at the partial
pressure. Now it's the
dissolved version which means
it's part of the partial
pressure of CO2 that on
average in the body is 40
millimeters mercury you
multiply it by the proportion
of the gas which is
0.07 and then you arrive
at five percent this
slide depicts the co2
content in milliliters per
liter versus the partial
pressure of co2 in
millimeters mercury and
it compares two versions
of hemoglobin it compares
the oxygenated version
of hemoglobin with a
deoxygenated version of
hemoglobin well why are
we looking at this at all
um well it is surprising
because we said that
the binding site for co2
and oxygen on hemoglobin
are not the same so why
would one then um inform
the binding of the other
well the short answer
is the halden effect so
when either predominantly
oxygen or co2 is bound
to hemoglobin it changes
the confirmation of the
entire hemoglobin molecule
and that is exactly what
the halden effect describes
and that facilitates co2
uptake by the oxy hemoglobin
let's briefly look again
at our graph so here we
have oxy hemoglobin that's
oxygenated hemoglobin that
would be the kind of
hemoglobin that has just picked
up oxygen in the lungs and
there it makes sense that
this hemoglobin does not
bind additional co2 molecules
if anything at all that's
where it wants to get rid
of co2 so that we can
blow it off whereas the
deoxygenated hemoglobin we would
predominantly find in target
tissue sites such as
active muscle that has just
produced a lot of CO2 due
to metabolism, and there
it's a good idea to have
hemoglobin pick up extra CO2.
We already know that the
majority of carbon dioxide
is carried as part of the
bicarbonate buffer system
in the blood, and here we
have an example where a target
tissue such as a very
active muscle has produced
a lot of co2 that co2 diffuses
out of the muscle into
the bloodstream and then
into the red blood cell so
the co2 goes into the blood
cell but it doesn't bind
to the red blood cell that's
why it's still part of
the partial pressure of co2
remember that there inside
the red blood cell it
combines with water and to
form carbonic acid that is
done by the enzyme carbonic
anhydrase which is associated
with red blood cells
and then the same
enzyme then facilitates
the reaction further
from carbonic
acid to bicarbonate
and hydrogen ion.
Then the bicarbonate is
released into the plasma and
to ensure electron neutrality
a negatively charged
chloride ion is being
taken up into the red blood
cell. So please note that
bicarbonate is negatively
charged so is chloride
ion and this process of
exchanging one versus the
other we also call the chloride
shift so it's an anion
exchanger and it's done by
a protein called the
band 3 protein um another
substance to pay attention
to is this hydrogen ion here
and so fortunately um
this particularly deoxy
hemoglobin is a very
good buffer for hydrogen
ions So, let's say we're
still in this area here
where a lot of metabolism
occurred, then that's
where we find a lot of
these hydrogen ions.
And at the same time,
because hemoglobin has just
delivered oxygen to the
site, it has turned into
deoxyhemoglobin. And the
oxyhemoglobin just has a
conformation that binds much
more tightly to hydrogen
ion than oxyhemoglobin. So
it's like a magnet thing.
The reverse of these reactions
happens in lung tissue.
So you can see by the
double arrows that all of
these processes are reversible.
so in lung tissue the
opposite happens and that
allows our body then to blow
off the co2 that was
generated via metabolism and
another question for you so
the vignette deals with a
19 year old college track
athlete who's competing in a
high-intensity 400 meter
sprint midway through the
race his activity his
actively contracting skeletal
muscle experience a sharp
increase in metabolic rate
rapidly producing large
quantities of carbon dioxide and
lactic acid lowering ph
which generates local heat
which of the following
best describes the
physiological shift occurring
in the hemoglobin oxygen
dissociation curve within
this localized muscle
tissue and what's its
functional benefit it.
So question number
one to you is, should
it become easier to
unload oxygen from
hemoglobin or should it
become more difficult?
Well, the muscle is in a
state of high oxygen demand.
So it would be good
if it became easier
for the muscle to obtain
that oxygen that's
bound to hemoglobin,
and that is associated
with a left-ward or
right-ward shift.
It's associated with a right
-ward shift. So, and that,
you know, makes answers B
and D potentially correct.
Let's look at all
of them. A left-ward
shift A, which increases
hemoglobin's affinity
for oxygen to ensure
that muscle tissue
absorbs gas faster,
is not true because,
you know, a leftward shift
makes it more difficult
for hemoglobin to unload
oxygen and also then more
difficult for the muscle to
obtain it so it has to be a
rightward shift which is
also called a bore shift
which decreases hemoglobin's
affinity for oxygen
facilitating its unloading to
the oxygen starved muscle so
b in this case is the correct
answer what are factors
that cause the bore shift
well we have this in the
vignette we have high carbon
dioxide uh we have low
ph so build up of lactic
acid we have increased heat
um and then there's another
factor two three dpg um
like a metabolite those all
facilitate the rightward
shift called bore shift um
and just as a note that goes
with a tout state of
hemoglobin so that's something
that you look at that
you look at later so when
hemoglobin tightens up um that
actually goes with an easier
release of oxygen kind
of makes sense you know
tightening up means less
space for stuff to bind that
releases oxygen faster so um
in other words in a relaxed
state hemoglobin holds on
more tightly to oxygen um
let's look at c leftward
shift we already said that's
not the correct answer it's
rightward shift it also says
that the leftward shift
leads to uh the formation
of the relaxed state um
you know which prevents the
premature release of oxygen
so we want the more premature
release so we want the
right shift the right which
if which binds oxygen more
tightly to hemoglobin to
protect the red blood cells
from acidic denaturation um
that's not true right which
shift releases oxygen more
easily and then e no shift
occurs because of systemic
bariceptor automatically
just cardiac output to keep
local tissue curves completely
constant so the cardiac
output here is unrelated
to the biochemical
functioning of hemoglobin so
the correct answer here is b
i'm repeating myself here
but please remember that i'm
staring very close to the
Constanza Physiology book.
Also a good time to
remind you again of the
summary portion of the
chapter being very good.
There are also self-quizzing
questions that are not
medical board style, but
they hit on all of the
important concepts that you
need to know. And at the end
of the book is a section
where you can look up your
answer if you're so inclined
please let me know what
you thought of this so
I'm always happy for some
feedback if it's positive
feedback that's marvelous
if there's anything that
I could have done a better
job with let me know thank
you and see you next time